<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>icews on Andreas Beger</title>
    <link>https://www.andybeger.com/tags/icews/</link>
    <description>Recent content in icews on Andreas Beger</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.andybeger.com/tags/icews/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A quick look at the public ICEWS data</title>
      <link>https://www.andybeger.com/2015/04/08/a-quick-look-at-the-public-icews-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.andybeger.com/2015/04/08/a-quick-look-at-the-public-icews-data/</guid>
      <description>The ICEWS data, including the underlying raw event data as well as some aggregations, were quietly posted on Dataverse the Friday before last. I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with the ICEWS data for several years now, first when I was working on on the ICEWS package&amp;ndash;we deliver updated monthly forecasts for the ICEWS events of interest (EOIs) once a month&amp;ndash;and more recently for the [irregular leadership change forecasting project](http://andybeger.com/2014/05/23/the-thailand-coup-and-some-recent- forecasting-work/). The public data are formatted differently from the data I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with, so most of the code I have lying around is not that useful, but in going through the public data I did recreate a short overview that is nowhere near as complete as David Masad&amp;rsquo;s first look (using Python), and some code that might be useful for getting started in R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking over the world</title>
      <link>https://www.andybeger.com/2013/10/18/taking-over-the-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.andybeger.com/2013/10/18/taking-over-the-world/</guid>
      <description>I work as a Postdoctoral Fellow in the Ward Lab here at Duke University. The Lab currently consists of Mike Ward, me, and a group of very smart graduate students. There are a lot of exciting projects within the lab, like ICEWS and other work for the US government, but also a broader set of projects by our lab members. One of the things we wanted to do this semester is to publicize this work a little bit more, and to this end we&amp;rsquo;re taking a new blog live today: Predictive Heuristics.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
