<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>forecasts on Andreas Beger</title>
    <link>https://www.andybeger.com/tags/forecasts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in forecasts on Andreas Beger</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.andybeger.com/tags/forecasts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Coup forecasts for 2017</title>
      <link>https://www.andybeger.com/2017/02/10/coup-forecasts-for-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.andybeger.com/2017/02/10/coup-forecasts-for-2017/</guid>
      <description>Forecasts Models and accuracy  Accuracy  Data  Covariates Coups Missing data Why did we not include…?  Parting thoughts   This posts provides some background for the coup forecasts article Mike Ward and I published in the Washington Posts’ Monkey Cage.
Coup attempts, even if they fail, as the events in Turkey since July 2016 have shown, can have a major impact on a country. And, as some of the reactions to the Turkey coup attempt have reiterated, they often seem to come as a surprise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When forecasting goes wrong (maybe): Yemen</title>
      <link>https://www.andybeger.com/2015/09/24/when-forecasting-goes-wrong-maybe-yemen/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.andybeger.com/2015/09/24/when-forecasting-goes-wrong-maybe-yemen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From the &lt;a href=&#34;http://predictiveheuristics.com/2015/08/10/yemen-investigation/&#34;&gt;Ward Lab blog&lt;/a&gt; a few weeks ago:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past few months we have worked on regularly updating our irregular leadership change models and forecasts in order to provide monthly 6-month ahead forecasts of the probability of irregular leadership change in a large number of countries&amp;ndash;but excluding the US&amp;ndash;worldwide. Part of that effort has been the occasional glance back at our previous predictions, and particularly more in-depth examinations for notable cases that we missed or got right, to see whether we can improve our modeling as a result. This note is one of these glances back: a postmortem of our Yemen predictions for the first half of 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
